Last thing to note here,
and this is really true
against any exercise program,
for any goal, is we have to understand
how we're modifying and really
be intentional and judicious
about all seven of the
modifiable variables.
If you've not heard that phrase before,
I would recommend checking
out my guest series
with Dr. Andrew Huberman
on the Huberman Lab podcast
I did in 2023, and we
talked about them in detail.
So to go through them quickly here,
I use an acronym developed
by my former colleague
and lab mate, Dr. Lee Brown,
which is called COFIVRP.
It's a wonderful acronym.
Scientists are always great
at developing acronyms.
But it stands for choice,
which is exercise choice,
so what exercises are you selecting?
This includes equipment as
well as what movement patterns,
and a lot of the things I
just discussed a second ago.
So the choice of the
exercise you're selecting
influences in part what
adaptation you're going to get:
strength and power or hypertrophy.
O, which stands for order,
it's another way of what
order do I do them in.
So what exercise goes first
in my day, second, third,
fourth, fifth, et cetera.
In the case of things
like strength and power,
order is incredibly important.
You need to be hyperspecific.
With hypertrophy, it's far less important.
The next one is V for volume.
This is how many repetitions
multiplied by how many
sets throughout the week.
So what's my total
weekly or monthly volume?
Again, as I said a second ago,
it's important in both categories here,
that we're paying attention,
but really, we need to make sure
that we're not losing volume
over time with hypertrophy.
And for strength we just want to make sure
we're not doing so much volume
that it's compromising
our ability to come back
and use high force and high power
in our next training session,
because those are the
ultimate drivers, generally,
for those adaptations.
The next is I for intensity,
and that refers to, again,
what percentage of your
one repetition maximum
you're going after.
It's the inverse answer to
what I just said a second ago,
where intensity needs to be
key for power and strength
and where it is important,
but far less relevant for
actual muscle hypertrophy.
F stands for frequency. This
is how many days per week.
Easy distinction here.
When you're training for hypertrophy,
you don't necessarily want
to train the same muscle
on multiple days in a row,
because you need to allow some recovery.
Now, where a lot of people
actually make the mistake here,
you don't need the muscles
to have complete rest.
It doesn't need to be
completely turned off
for two or three days.
As you'll see in the
program, it's not needed,
but you definitely don't
want to work it hard
multiple days in a row
in your typical fashion.
Strength and power is the opposite.
You can train the same
muscles every single day.
As you'll see, the program does.
Not a problem here,
because there's not a
lot of residual fatigue,
not a lot of local fatigue,
rather like in the actual muscle,
not a lot of soreness
because we're not pushing that adaptation.
And so frequency can be very different
between these two programs and should be.
Strength and power requires practice,
which means more repetitions,
which means a lot more frequently.
R stands for rest, which
is your rest interval.
How much time am I taking
between sets or even repetitions?
You have the option: for
hypertrophy, can be low rest,
say 30 seconds of rest,
or maybe even less,
all the way up to five minutes of rest;
but for strength and power, almost always,
you need to have a minimum
of three minutes of rest,
because again we're going
after something different here.
This is really about the quality
of each individual movement,
and so if we're keeping
ourselves to a short rest
and we're losing our
force or power production,
then we're losing our actual goal,
which means we're not going
to get what we're after.
There are exceptions to all these rules,
but this is just a standard default
of typically what we're trying to do.
The last variable here
stands for P, progression,
which is how are we progressing
these things over time?
And that is really what
we're going to talk about
along the way.
[music]